<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The dead saint speaking, or, A sermon preached upon occasion of the death of that eminent man, Mr. Mathew Newcomen ... wherein is succinctly discoursed (to a popular auditory in Dedham) what instructions are given and sealed to the living by the death of the righteous servants of God / by J.F., Minister of the Gospel.</title>
            <author>Fairfax, John, 1623-1700.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 56 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A39761</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F127</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16035</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13149622</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13149622</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98090</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A39761)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98090)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 416:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The dead saint speaking, or, A sermon preached upon occasion of the death of that eminent man, Mr. Mathew Newcomen ... wherein is succinctly discoursed (to a popular auditory in Dedham) what instructions are given and sealed to the living by the death of the righteous servants of God / by J.F., Minister of the Gospel.</title>
                  <author>Fairfax, John, 1623-1700.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A.M. and R.R. for Edward Giles ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Written by John Fairfax. Cf. Halkett &amp; Laing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Newcomen, Matthew, 1610?-1669.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98090:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98090:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98090:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98090:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Dead Saint Speaking.</hi> OR, A SERMON PREACHED Upon <hi>Occaſion</hi> of the Death of that Eminent Man, Mr. <hi>MATHEW NEWCOMEN,</hi> Sometimes <hi>Miniſter of the Goſpel</hi> at <hi>Dedham</hi> in <hi>Eſſex:</hi> Who dyed at <hi>LEYDEN.</hi> Wherein is <hi>ſuccinctly</hi> diſcourſed (to a popular Auditory in <hi>Dedham</hi>) what <hi>Inſtructions</hi> are given and <hi>ſealed</hi> to the Living, by the Death of the <hi>righteous Servants of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>J. F.</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Prov. 10.7.</bibl>
               <p>The memory of the juſt is bleſſed.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pſal. 116.15.</bibl>
               <p>Precious in the ſight of the Lord is the death of his Saints.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>A. M.</hi> and <hi>R. R.</hi> for <hi>Edward Giles,</hi> Bookſeller in St. <hi>Andrews</hi> Pariſh in <hi>Norwich.</hi> 1679.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:98090:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98090:3"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>I Know not how I am induced to prefix a few lines to this <hi>Anonymous</hi> diſcourſe, unleſs from the great kindneſs I have to the <hi>memory</hi> of that <hi>Reverend perſon,</hi> whoſe death gave occaſion to it. A perſon whom I had the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs to be acquainted with for the ſpace of about thirty years; during which time, and ſince that time, I have had the happineſs to be acquainted with very many <hi>learned</hi> and <hi>pious men.</hi> But this I ſhall ſay, I never knew any that excelled him, conſidering him as a <hi>Miniſter in the Pulpit,</hi> a <hi>Diſputant in the Schools,</hi> and a <hi>deſirable companion.</hi> In the firſt capacity, his <hi>gift in prayer</hi> was <hi>incomparable:</hi> He was a <hi>ſolid, painful, pathetick</hi> and <hi>perſwaſive</hi> Preacher. I have often thought, that if <hi>Moral Suaſion</hi> would have done the work, (though God bleſſed him with very many, yet) he would have had many more Converts than he had. I have known very few his fellows, either in <hi>pleading</hi> with God on the behalf of men, or with <hi>men on the behalf of God;</hi> he had the true abilities and <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of a Preacher: He ſucceeded that great man, Mr. <hi>John Rogers</hi> of <hi>Dedham;</hi> of whom I remember what himſelf ſaid in his Verſes he made up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Death (whiles I was a School-boy in the Town),
<q>
                  <l>Since <hi>Peters</hi> days, ſcarce ever any</l>
                  <l>Fir'd ſo many.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>But their gifts were very different. Mr. <hi>Rogers</hi> was a <hi>grave, ſevere, ſolid Divine;</hi> his <hi>great gift</hi> lay in a peculiar <hi>geſture, action, and behaviour, in the delivery of what ſolid matter he
<pb facs="tcp:98090:4"/> had prepared;</hi> ſo as few heard him without trembling <hi>at the Word of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>Reverend perſons gifts</hi> lay almoſt all ways; and his worſt enemies muſt ſay he ſhewed as much <hi>Art</hi> as <hi>Piety</hi> in his Sermons and Prayers, and all Religious Services; he was a <hi>moſt accompliſhed Scholar and Chriſtian.</hi> His <hi>Sermon</hi> preached before the Parliament upon <hi>Novemb. 5. 1641,</hi> His <hi>Irenicum;</hi> indeed, whatever of his appear'd to the World ſpeak him ſuch a one, as none can diſpute his want of Learning, without bringing their own in queſtion. His managery of the Argument againſt the <hi>Toleration of the Jews</hi> (though never printed) made him admired by all that heard it. Take him in his ordinary converſe, he was <hi>pleaſant, facetious,</hi> of <hi>extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary humility, affability,</hi> and <hi>courteſie;</hi> his whole con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation was both <hi>pious</hi> and <hi>amiable.</hi> After he had under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken the charge of the <hi>Church of God</hi> in <hi>Dedham,</hi> (which was immediately upon the death of Mr. <hi>Rogers</hi>) he would liſten to no temptation to any other place, though he had both many and great offers, but there continued till a <hi>legal death</hi> deprived them of him, <hi>Anno 1662.</hi> After this, in a ſhort time, he was invited to the <hi>Paſtoral Charge of the Church</hi> at <hi>Ley<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den;</hi> he was pleaſed to entertain ſeveral diſcourſes with me (though much his inferiour, ſuch was his great humility) about his going. I was no great incourager of his acceptance of it; that which prevailed with him, was, that there he ſhould have the <hi>publick liberty of his Miniſtry,</hi> which he preferred to any thing beſides in this world; there he finiſhed the remaining part of his courſe, exceeding acceptable to Dr. <hi>Hoornbeck,</hi> and other of the <hi>Profeſſors</hi> there. He was pleaſed to maintain a correſpondence with me by Letters; and the laſt Letter (if I remember right) which I received from him, if I miſtook him not, hinted ſome thoughts of his return into <hi>England;</hi> not find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that ſatisfaction in all points there to himſelf, which he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he went hoped for. But the Lord prevented him, taking him to himſelf by a <hi>Fever,</hi> which prevailed much in that City,
<pb facs="tcp:98090:4"/> and ſwept away many in the year <hi>1668, or 1669,</hi> (I forgot which). This Sermon was afterwards preached in that which ſometimes was his Pulpit in <hi>Dedham,</hi> by a <hi>Reverend</hi> and <hi>Learned perſon.</hi> I cannot ſay I know not the perſon; but think it not reaſonable to fetch him out of his Covert; who although yet alive, is not willing to diſcover himſelf. I ſhall only ſay, that he is a <hi>Workman who needs not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed.</hi> Whoſo readeth this popular diſcourſe, will eaſily conclude him a man of excellent Parts, and great Piety. It had been no great difficulty to him to have ſtuft his Sermon with <hi>Quotations out of Authors,</hi> or to have dreſſed it up with ſix-footed words, and a lofty ſtile; if he had judged, that that <hi>Language of men puft up,</hi> had been proper for a Countrey Auditory, (how judicious ſoever) or could have judged that <hi>folly of Preaching,</hi> to have been that <hi>fooliſhneſs of Preaching</hi> mentioned by the Apoſtle, by <hi>which God hath choſen to ſave elect ſouls.</hi> I remember <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaid of <hi>Cyprian,</hi> he once preached at that rate, to ſhew <hi>he could do it;</hi> but <hi>never but once, to ſhew he would not.</hi> This <hi>Reverend Author</hi> (although a very learned man) knew that an <hi>Iron key</hi> was better to open a Lock (it is <hi>Auguſtines</hi> metaphor) than <hi>one of Gold.</hi> Thou wilt, Reader, find here, what is <hi>ſcriptural, pious, profitable,</hi> and that clothed with a <hi>decent language,</hi> and ſuch a diſcovery of <hi>Wit</hi> and <hi>Art</hi> as will make thee underſtand; the <hi>Author,</hi> if he had pleaſed, as to thoſe little things of <hi>wit</hi> and <hi>phraſe,</hi> could have outdone what is here, but choſe to do no more for oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of himſelf, that he might the more profit his ordinary Readers Souls. I could have wiſhed the Author would have himſelf dreſſed it up for the <hi>Preſs,</hi> but he rather choſe to be <hi>ſtudying new Sermons,</hi> than trimming up old ones. It is not his, but ſome Auditors importunity that hath brought it to the light, and I ſhould have checkt my ſelf in helping the least toward it, but for my fondneſs to have any thing publick that might tell the world, the worth of ſo worthy
<pb facs="tcp:98090:5"/> a perſon, ſo much my intimate friend; and what <hi>England</hi> and the <hi>Reformed part of the World</hi> loſt that day in which Heaven gained this Eminent Servant of God, to whoſe Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory it is dedicated. This will tell thee how he <hi>being dead, yet ſpeaketh.</hi> The Lord give us all an <hi>hearing ear,</hi> and an <hi>heart willing to learn.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy faithful Friend in the Work of the Goſpel, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98090:5"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>HEB. XI. 4.</bibl>
                  <p>—By it he being dead, yet ſpeaketh.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THIS <hi>Chapter</hi> is a ſhort <hi>Martyrology:</hi> An <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome</hi> of the <hi>Acts and Monuments</hi> of the Church of Old; wherein by an Apoſtolical hand, gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Divine Spirit, a true and faithful Record, a good and honourable Report is made of the noble <hi>Acts, Victories,</hi> and <hi>Triumphs</hi> of the faith of the ancient <hi>Patriarchs, Prophets</hi> and <hi>Martyrs,</hi> the Worthies of God, of <hi>whom the world was not worthy.</hi> Among theſe <hi>Abel</hi> hath the Priority, and leads the <hi>Van;</hi> to the honour of whoſe faith three Things are here ſpoken.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The <hi>excellency of his ſacrifice above his Brothers: By faith Abel offered unto God a more excellent ſacrifice than Cain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>The juſtification of his perſon in the ſight of God:</hi> By which faith he obtained witneſs that he was righteous, God teſtifying of his Gifts.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The <hi>preciouſneſs of his memory,</hi> the voice and virtue of his remembrance after death. <hi>By it he being dead, yet ſpeaketh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This laſt, as being ſuitable to our occaſion, ſhall be the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of our diſcourſe, which muſt be not according to the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the occaſion, but according to the weakneſs of the <hi>Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,</hi> and the ſhort time you thought fit to allow me for this ſolemn ſervice.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By it he being dead, yet ſpeaketh.</hi> At the very firſt read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:98090:6"/> of theſe words there may ſeem a <hi>paradox</hi> in the Text, much greater than in the Pulpit; Behold! here a perſon <hi>naturally dead, Abel,</hi> the ſecond man that was born into the world, and the firſt that dyed, having been dead now <hi>five thouſand years</hi> and upward, <hi>he yet ſpeaketh.</hi> The dead are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed altogether <hi>deaf,</hi> they cannot hear, there is no ſpeaking to them: in vain are <hi>prayers and ſupplications</hi> made to Saints departed. <hi>Abraham is ignorant of us, and Iſrael knoweth us not:</hi> they are as deaf to their Petitioners, as <hi>Baal</hi> to his <hi>Prieſts;</hi> but yet they are not altogether <hi>dumb,</hi> they may, and they do <hi>ſpeak,</hi> not <hi>formaliter,</hi> not <hi>vitally</hi> and <hi>ſyllabically,</hi> by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of the <hi>throat, tongue, teeth</hi> and <hi>lips</hi> (as a living man doth) but <hi>effective &amp; eminenter,</hi> in effect, comprehenſively, as the man is ſaid to <hi>ſpeak with his feet,</hi> Prov. 6.13. <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal ſpeech</hi> is that which holds forth ſomewhat to the <hi>ears of others,</hi> which is to be known and underſtood by them. Now when a viſible <hi>argumentative</hi> ſignification of ſuch things is made to us by the dead, then are they ſaid to <hi>ſpeak</hi> what the living do learn, or may learn, or ought to learn from the dead, that the dead ſpeak; <hi>Being dead, he yet ſpeaketh;</hi> the word may be rendred <hi>paſſively,</hi> he is yet ſpoken of; he being dead, there is an honourable mention made of him.</p>
            <p>The <hi>active</hi> ſenſe ſeems more probable, but we ſhall not exclude the <hi>paſſive; Abel being dead, he yet ſpeaketh.</hi> What! is this peculiarly attributed to <hi>Abel?</hi> Is he the only man that ſpeaketh? and are all the reſt dumb? No, what is here ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of <hi>Abel,</hi> is common unto others; but it is peculiarly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed unto <hi>Abel</hi> for a double reaſon.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe <hi>Abel</hi> was the <hi>firſt dead;</hi> it is ſpoken of <hi>Abel</hi> as the firſt, as the <hi>repreſentative</hi> of all that follow in the eſtate and condition of <hi>Abel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. It is peculiarly attributed to <hi>Abel,</hi> becauſe it is eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally recorded of him, that after his death he ſpeaketh. <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.10, <hi>The voice of thy brothers blood crieth unto me from the ground.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:98090:6"/>
            <p>
               <hi>That dead Saints do yet ſpeak,</hi> is the general truth from the Text, which is peculiarly exemplified in the inſtance of <hi>Abel: Abel being dead, yet ſpeaketh. Speaking</hi> in the Text, muſt be underſtood in a ſenſe of <hi>eminency</hi> and <hi>dignity,</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſomewhat worthy to be heard and obſerved. This is not an attribute to be allowed to every dead perſon. Alas! what do the ignorant, worldling, debaſed, debauched, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane generation of men being dead, ſpeak? They ſpeak, it may be as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſaith, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36.1, <hi>The tranſgreſſion of the wicked ſaith within my heart, There is no fear of God before his eyes.</hi> They ſpeak <hi>folly, vanity, violence, wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> and <hi>forgetfulneſs</hi> of <hi>God;</hi> nothing elſe do they ſpeak worthy to be heard. God indeed ſometimes by his remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Providences, and ſome notorious Judgments, makes them to ſpeak when they are dead, but as a <hi>wrecked Ship</hi> upon the Sands or Rocks ſpeak unto the Mariners that is in a dangerous Sea or Voyage; ſo <hi>Achan</hi> being dead, ſpoke unto the covetous; <hi>Zimry</hi> and <hi>Cozby</hi> ſpeak unto the <hi>adulterer;</hi> ſo <hi>Herod</hi> being dead, ſpeaks to the proud; ſo <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira</hi> ſpeak to the lyars; but of themſelves, freely, dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctly, and intentionally, they ſpeak nothing, they are ſilent in the grave, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.17. They neither ſpeak to the profit of others, nor are they ſpoken of to their own honour: This is the honour of the Saints of God, to ſpeak when they are dead. <hi>By faith Abel being dead, yet ſpeaketh;</hi> By the precious Graces with which the Saints are enriched; by the holy life they have expreſſed; by the good works they have wrought; by the pious examples they have ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their generation; by the eminent ſervice they have done to God and his Church; by their ſharp tryals and temptations; by their bitter Sufferings and Martyrdoms, wherein they have been more than Conquerors: By theſe the Saints, being dead, yet ſpeak: they ſpeak to purpoſe, for the vindication of truth, to the ſhame of wickedneſs; they ſpeak to the honour of Religion; they ſpeak to the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98090:7"/> furtherance of the Goſpel; they ſpeak to the <hi>conviction, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, inſtruction, edification,</hi> and <hi>ſalvation</hi> of the <hi>living:</hi> they ſpeak to the <hi>glory of God.</hi> This general truth we ſhall ſpeak of in the particular inſtance of <hi>Abel: Abel being dead, yet ſpeaketh:</hi> he ſpeaketh to us, and he ſpeaks to God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abel</hi> ſpeaks to us in a <hi>fivefold reſpect,</hi> or under a <hi>fivefold conſideration. Abel</hi> yet ſpeaks. <hi>Abel,</hi> a <hi>man</hi> being dead, yet ſpeaks. <hi>Abel,</hi> a <hi>believer,</hi> being dead, yet ſpeaks. <hi>Abel,</hi> a <hi>worſhipper of God,</hi> being dead, yet ſpeaketh. <hi>Abel,</hi> a <hi>Prieſt or Teacher,</hi> being dead, yet ſpeaketh. <hi>Abel,</hi> a <hi>Martyr,</hi> being dead, yet ſpeaketh.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Abel,</hi> a <hi>man,</hi> being dead, yet ſpeaketh; and this is it he ſpeaks, he ſpeaks death to us all. Oh my Brethren and Siſters, the Sons and Daughters of my Father <hi>Adam;</hi> ye are all mortals, mortality is your property; there is a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of corruption in you, and death haſtneth. <hi>Duſt thou art, and to duſt thou ſhalt return,</hi> ſaid God to <hi>Adam, Gen.</hi> 3.19. <hi>Probatum eſt,</hi> ſaith <hi>Abel,</hi> being dead; Gods word is truth, take me for an inſtance. <hi>Abel,</hi> vanity is the ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it, and that is my name. <hi>Every man at his beſt estate is altogether vanity,</hi> Pſal. 39. Particularly, <hi>Abel</hi> a man <hi>being dead, yet ſpeaketh:</hi> He ſpeaketh unto the young man, death may overtake thee in thy youth: <hi>Abel,</hi> he might be forty, or fifty, or ſixty years of age when he dyed; but this was a young man then; that was a ſmall age in that age of the world, when the age of man was ſeven, or eight, or nine hundred years, or upward. Why then, what aſſurance canſt thou have, that thou art far from death, who in the courſe of nature haſt forty or fifty years to live before thee, when <hi>Abel</hi> is cut off from the land of the living, who had in the ſame courſe of nature as many hundreds of years of life before him, as thou haſt half ſcores?</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Abel,</hi> a <hi>man</hi> being dead, ſpeaketh to the <hi>ſtrong:</hi> Death may overcome thee in thy ſtrength. No queſtion but <hi>Abel</hi> was come to ſtrength of years, and that age was much
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:98090:7"/> ſtronger than this, when out of the loins of one, the imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate iſſue might be an hundred-fold and more. What then ſpeaks <hi>Abel,</hi> being dead? <hi>Glory not, O strong man, in thy strength.</hi> Remember thy beauty, thy vigour, thy maturity, thy marrow and fatneſs, the courage of thy heart, the ſtout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and ſtraitneſs of thy body, the dexterity of thine arms and legs, cannot withſtand the aſſaulting enemy, but muſt yield up themſelves to the force of prevailing death.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Abel,</hi> a man <hi>being dead, yet ſpeaketh; he ſpeaketh to the ſecure and unprovided;</hi> death may ſurprize thee unawares. <hi>Abel</hi> in the Field; <hi>Abel</hi> about the works of his Calling; <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel</hi> converſing with his Brother; <hi>Abel,</hi> to whom death was ſo much a ſtranger, that he never ſaw it; who would have thought that <hi>Abel</hi> went out into the field to dye? Thus <hi>Abel</hi> was taken in his <hi>calling, Nabal</hi> in his <hi>feasting, Belteſhazzar</hi> in his <hi>cups, Herod</hi> in his <hi>pomp;</hi> the rich fool promiſing himſelf eaſe and merriment, all ſpake the ſame thing.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And laſtly, <hi>Abel,</hi> a man, being dead, yet ſpeaketh un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all; <hi>Death may kill thee with thine own weapon.</hi> A bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is born for adverſity; a brother is born for a help in danger, for a defence and ſafeguard; Oh, but yet by a bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth <hi>Abel</hi> dye. What then ſpeaks <hi>Abel,</hi> being dead? Why, ſo frail is thy life, that thy food, thy phyſick, thy houſe, thy horſe, thy ſword, thy ſervant, thy friend, thy brother, yea, thy ſelf may be thy death. <hi>Abel,</hi> a man, being dead, yet ſpeaketh.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Abel</hi> a <hi>believer,</hi> being dead, yet ſpeaketh. What ſpeaks he? He ſpeaks,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The grace of God to be most free:</hi> he hath mercy on whom he will have mercy. It is Grace that makes the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between one man and another. <hi>Abel</hi> and <hi>Cain,</hi> both Children of one and the ſame Father, both lying together in one and the ſame womb, as twins probably, both par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of one and the ſame means, both commended to God in one and the ſame prayer: <hi>Abel</hi> the younger, and <hi>Cain</hi> the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98090:8"/> elder, and yet behold <hi>Abel</hi> is a believer, and <hi>Cain</hi> is a mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer; <hi>Abel</hi> is loved, and <hi>Cain</hi> is hated; <hi>Abel</hi> righteous, and <hi>Cain</hi> wicked; <hi>Abel</hi> is juſtified, and <hi>Cain</hi> is condemned; <hi>Abel</hi> the Child of God, and <hi>Cain</hi> a Child of the Devil. What ſpeaks <hi>Abel,</hi> being dead, but this, That grace makes the difference.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Abel</hi> a <hi>believer,</hi> being dead, yet ſpeaketh. <hi>Righteouſneſs is by faith, not by works.</hi> By <hi>faith</hi> he obtained witneſs that he was <hi>righteous. Cain</hi> had his works, but he had no faith. <hi>Cain</hi> ſacrificed, but <hi>believed not. Cain</hi> is <hi>unrighteous. Cain</hi> is condemned. <hi>Abel</hi> hath <hi>works and faith too. Abel offereth</hi> and <hi>believeth. Abel</hi> is righteous, he is juſtified, God hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect unto <hi>Abel.</hi> Juſtification is by faith.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Abel</hi> a <hi>believer,</hi> being dead, yet ſpeaketh; <hi>That it is a happy advantage to live under means. Abel</hi> believed, Whence hath he his faith? from God as the Author, from God as the principle: But what, without means? No, <hi>Abel</hi> had the <hi>hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py instruction of a Father,</hi> and he was taught the law by a <hi>holy Mother.</hi> The Patriarchs were <hi>Priests and Prophets</hi> in their own families. <hi>Adam</hi> taught his Children the fear of the Lord. <hi>Abel</hi> then being dead, yet ſpeaks this in the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of the New Teſtament; <hi>Faith comes by hearing, and hearing by the word of God;</hi> bleſſed are they that hear the joyful ſound thereof.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Abel</hi> a believer, being dead, yet ſpeaketh this, <hi>That the grace of God doth not priviledg from the greatest croſſes;</hi> of all evils, death is the foreſt, death is the moſt grievous. <hi>Skin for skin, and all that a man hath will he give for his life,</hi> was a truth, though a lyar ſpoke it. <hi>Abel,</hi> a Saint in grace, and in favour with God, yet he dyed: he dyed a violent death, by the hand of his brother. <hi>It was not an enemy, then I could have born it,</hi> (ſaith <hi>David</hi>) <hi>neither was it he that hated me, that lifted up his hand against me: but thou, O man, my brother, mine equal, mine acquaintance:</hi> this was the wounding of his heart. What ſpeaks he? If grace ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empts
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98090:8"/> not from death, from ſuch a death, with ſuch circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, much leſs from leſſer evils: <hi>God ſcourgeth every ſon whom he receiveth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Laſtly, <hi>Abel</hi> a believer being dead, yet ſpeaketh; What? <hi>The greatest croſſes ſhall not make void the grace of God. Abel died,</hi> he is <hi>bel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ved of God still; Abel</hi> dyed, he is righteous <hi>Abel</hi> ſtill; he ſpeaks this, That God knows the ſouls of his Saints in their adverſities. God chuſeth the Saints in the furnace of affliction: He tells their wandrings, and puts their tears into his bottle: The ſupplication of the Saints come before him, their deſires and their groans are not hid from him. Thus <hi>Abel</hi> a believer, being dead, yet ſpeaketh.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Abel</hi> a <hi>worſhipper of God being dead, yet ſpeaketh;</hi> what ſpeaks he as a <hi>worſhipper of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>God is to be worſhipped by us:</hi> His holy example ſpeaks this, God is to be worſhipped as the Author of our beings, as the <hi>Lord of our lives,</hi> as the Father of our ſpirits, as the God of our mercies, as our King and Lawgiver, the Mighty, the Almighty <hi>Jehovah,</hi> our <hi>Saviour</hi> and <hi>Redeemer,</hi> whoſe we are, and who we ought to ſerve; we are not our own, not our own free-men, not <hi>independent beings,</hi> but we are made by the power of God, we are maintained by the providence of God, we are bought with the blood of God, we were ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the Law of God, we are bound by the Covenant of God, and therefore ought to live to the glory of God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Abel</hi> a worſhipper of God, being dead, yet ſpeaketh, <hi>That God that is to be worſhipped, is to be worſhipped by faith.</hi> By faith he offered a more excellent ſacrifice, by faith he wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped God. The worſhip of God in faith, is a worſhip of Gods own conſtitution. God is not to be worſhipped by mens inventions, but by his own appointments. God is to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped, not as we will, but as he commands.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Abel,</hi> as a worſhipper of God, being dead, yet ſpeaketh, <hi>That God is to be worſhipped with our beſt. Abel</hi> he brought of the <hi>firſtlings of his flock,</hi> of the fat thereof, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4. of the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98090:9"/> beſt. The laſt, or the leaſt, the torn, the blind, the lame, the weak, the ſick, the dregs of our beings, the weakneſs of our age, the deadneſs of our hearts, the coldneſs of our affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the exerciſe of our bodies; this alone is not to be offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto God, for he is a great King: but the kindneſs of our youth, the ripeneſs of our age, the ſtrength of our parts, the zeal of our affections, the intentions of our hearts, the health of our bodies, our whole hearts, all our ſouls, and all our ſtrength; the beſt improvement we can make of our ſelves, is an offering becoming the great God.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Abel,</hi> a worſhipper of God, being dead, yet ſpeaketh, <hi>That the beſt offerings that we make unto God, are not accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble but through a Mediator.</hi> God teſtified of <hi>Abels</hi> gifts, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were offered by faith through <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> The beſt we can tender to God, is not worthy of Gods accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as from us, but it muſt be recommended by the <hi>Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor;</hi> and without faith <hi>Cains</hi> offering ſignified nothing; God had no reſpect to <hi>Cain</hi> nor to his offering. Thus <hi>Abel</hi> as a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipper of God, being dead, yet ſpeaketh.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>Abel</hi> as a Prieſt or Teacher, being dead, yet ſpeaketh. It's very probable, that <hi>Abel</hi> had a diſtinct Family, as <hi>Cain</hi> alſo had; and each had their conſiderable ſtocks in the world, for they offered to God of their own; and ſo <hi>Abel</hi> in his Family was a <hi>prieſt</hi> and <hi>teacher.</hi> However, ſuppoſe <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel</hi> were yet remainining in the Family of his Father <hi>Adam,</hi> yet he was the eldeſt but one, born with <hi>Cain</hi> (proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly) and withal was the perſon next to <hi>Adam</hi> that was taught of God. <hi>Abel</hi> was a perſon inſtructed in the knowledg of <hi>Religion,</hi> and of a <hi>holy and exemplary life and converſation,</hi> and ſo he muſt needs be accounted a very uſeful Inſtrument for the hand of God to work by in the hearts of thoſe of that generation. <hi>Abel</hi> being dead yet ſpeaketh. What doth he ſpeak? He ſpeaks this, That God hath no need of the moſt hopeful and likely Inſtruments for
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98090:9"/> his Churches ſervice. Though <hi>Abel</hi> dye, the Church ſhall not dye, Religion ſhall not dye, no elect ſoul ſhall be loſt for want of <hi>Abel.</hi> The purpoſe of God ſhall ſtand. God is not beholden to means, much leſs to this means, or that, or ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, though never ſo likely. It is all one to an Almighty Power to ſave by means, or without means; to ſave by few Inſtruments, or by many; by weak Inſtruments, or by ſtrong. <hi>Joſeph</hi> was an eminent Inſtrument for the planting, for the protecting, for the providing for, for the ordering, advancing, and priviledging of the Family of <hi>Jacob,</hi> the Church of God in the Land of <hi>Egypt;</hi> but <hi>Joſeph</hi> is a mortal man, <hi>Joſeph</hi> muſt dye; What then? Muſt the Church of God fail in <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt?</hi> muſt <hi>Iſrael</hi> periſh in the Land of <hi>Ham?</hi> No certainly; <hi>Joſeph</hi> ſpake to his brethren, <hi>I dye;</hi> but what then? <hi>God ſhall ſurely viſit you.</hi> Gen. 50.24.</p>
            <p>Fifthly and laſtly, <hi>Abel</hi> a martyr being dead, yet ſpeaketh. What doth he ſpeak? He ſpeaks</p>
            <p n="1">1. As God ſpake, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15, <hi>I will put enmity between her ſeed and thy ſeed. Abel</hi> ſubſcribes the enmity between the ſeed of the woman and the ſeed of the Serpent, the Saint and the ſinner, the juſt and the unjuſt, the righteous and the unrighteous, the holy and the prophane; they are oppoſite one unto another, as light unto darkneſs, as life unto death, as eaſt unto weſt, as heaven unto hell. There can be no accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modation, no accord or agreement between them. <hi>What agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is between Chriſt and Belial?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Abel</hi> a martyr being dead yet ſpeaketh: What doth he ſpeak? even as our Saviour ſpeaks <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.21, <hi>The bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall deliver up the brother to death, and the father the child, and the child ſhall riſe up against the parents, and ſhall cauſe them to be put to death.</hi> There is no hatred like the hatred of Religion. This enmity of Religion it offereth vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to Nature, it breaketh the ſtrongeſt obligations; it blots out of a mans mind the memory of the Father that begat him, and the mother that bare him, and the paps that gave him
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:98090:10"/> ſuck: It forgetteth natural relation and affection, and deba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth man into a beaſt, a Devil incarnate; <hi>Mic.</hi> 7.6. there are many inſtances to the ſame purpoſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Abel</hi> a <hi>Martyr,</hi> being dead, yet ſpeaketh; and what ſpeaks he? as <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 Tim. 3.12, <hi>all that will live godly in Chriſt Jeſus, muſt ſuffer perſecution.</hi> Chriſt and the Croſs, Religion and Perſecution, Holineſs and Afflictions, theſe are bound together by a bond that cannot be broken. The Saints of God are ſtrangers in the world, and muſt expect to meet with hard things. The Saints of God are <hi>warriers</hi> and <hi>ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers</hi> under the banner of Jeſus Chriſt, againſt the world, and muſt expect ſometimes to meet with blows. The Saints of God are <hi>travellers</hi> in a ſtrange Countrey, they are <hi>travellers</hi> in a way towards their home, which is Heaven, and they muſt expect ſometimes to meet with dirty ways and foul wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Abel</hi> a martyr, being dead, yet ſpeaketh: What ſpeaks he? as <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 116.15. <hi>precious in the ſight of the Lord is the death of his Saints.</hi> The death of his martyred Saints eſpecially is precious. The death of his Saints is precious. The death of <hi>Abel</hi> was precious in the ſight of God: He takes ſpecial notice of it, <hi>Gen.</hi> 14.9,10. God preſently meets with <hi>Cain,</hi> and ſaith, <hi>Cain, where is thy brother Abel?</hi> What haſt thou done? God <hi>makes inquiſition for the blood of Abel;</hi> ay, but ſaith God unto <hi>Abel,</hi> being dead, Haſt thou loſt thy life for my ſake? Is thy blood ſhed for thy love un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me? I will avenge thee on thine enemy with eternal death, and recompence thee with eternal life.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Laſtly, <hi>Abel</hi> a <hi>Martyr,</hi> being dead, yet ſpeaketh. What ſpeaks he? as <hi>Paul,</hi> Acts 17.31, <hi>God hath appointed a day in which he will judg the world. Abels</hi> Martyrdom ſpeaks, That the wrongs and injuries done to the righteous, to the Saints of God in the world, do undoubtedly ſpeak, that there ſhall be a <hi>judgment-day, which is a manifest token of the righteous judgment of God, ſeeing it is a righteous thing with
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98090:10"/> God to render tribulation to them that trouble you.</hi> Violence and wrongs, injuries and oppreſſions, ſhall not always tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph as they do. God will one day cauſe Juſtice to take the Throne, and to reign over his enemies. Thus <hi>Abel</hi> being dead, yet ſpeaketh; as a man, as a believer, as a worſhipper of God, as a Teacher, as a Martyr.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Abel</hi> being dead, yet ſpeaketh: He ſpeaketh unto God.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He ſpeaketh to God, firſt by his <hi>prayers</hi> and <hi>ſupplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Abel,</hi> a worſhipper of God, no queſtion was a pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Saint, it was part of his worſhip; and his prayers yet ſpeak. We believe the communion of Saints, one conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable part whereof is this, a participiation of one anothers prayers. All the members of the Church, the Saints that follow after, they fare the better for thoſe that went be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            <p>The firſt age of the Church contributes to all ages follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and every particular believer contributes to the whole. The prayers of <hi>Abel</hi> for the Church of God that was to come, they are yet before the Lord; his eyes are yet upon them, as they are recorded upon the file in heaven: his ear is yet hearing them. By his prayers, <hi>Abel</hi> being dead, yet ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth unto God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Abel</hi> being dead, yet ſpeaketh unto God <hi>by his blood.</hi> When he was dead, ſaid God to <hi>Cain, The voice of thy bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers blood crieth unto me from the earth.</hi> The Martyrs blood, it crieth againſt <hi>Cain</hi> for vengeance, which is not yet fully executed; it cryes yet to God for himſelf, that God would make him reparation and ſatisfaction, that God would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore to him the life that <hi>Cain</hi> took away: it ſtill cries, and it ſhall cry until the day of Reſurrection. <hi>Abels</hi> blood yet crieth unto God; not only againſt <hi>Cain,</hi> but it cryeth unto God againſt all the <hi>generation of the Cainites,</hi> againſt all the perſecutors of the Church of God; for all perſecutors following, in reſpect of <hi>Abel,</hi> are as <hi>Saul,</hi> in reſpect of <hi>Stephen<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:98090:11"/> they are conſenting to his death. For had the preſent ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of perſecutors lived in the days of <hi>Abel,</hi> they would as well as <hi>Cain</hi> have imbrued their hands in the blood of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel.</hi> Tremble at this then, oh ye generation of perſecutors! <hi>Abels</hi> blood crieth unto God from the earth againſt you. The ſouls from under the <hi>altar</hi> of thoſe that were ſlain for the teſtimony of Jeſus, <hi>cry unto God perpetually, How long, Lord, holy and true, doſt thou not judg and avenge our blood on them that dwell on the earth?</hi> and what is it that they cry for unto the Lord, but that which our Saviour ſaid? <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.25. <hi>That upon theſe perſecutors may come all the righteous blood that hath been ſhed, from the blood of righteous Abel, unto the blood of the laſt martyr that ſhall be ſlain upon the earth. Abel</hi> being dead, he thus ſpeaketh unto us, and he thus ſpeaketh unto God.</p>
            <p>Take the words now in a <hi>paſſive</hi> ſenſe; <hi>Abel</hi> being dead, is yet ſpoken of: he obtained a good report, as it is ſaid <hi>ver.</hi> 2. He is ſpoken of by God in holy Writ, to the intent that he may be ſpoken of by man. God doth make an honourable mention of <hi>Abel,</hi> and therein commends him to his Church, that an honourable mention may be made of him; for where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever this Scripture ſhall be read and preached, this alſo that <hi>Abel</hi> hath done and ſuffered ſhall be ſpoken of, <hi>Abels</hi> Faith and Righteouſneſs; <hi>Abels</hi> good and holy Converſation; <hi>Abels</hi> Sufferings and Martyrdom ſhall be ſpoken of for an honourable memorial of him. <hi>The memory of the juſt is bleſſed,</hi> Prov. 10.7, <hi>but the name of the wicked ſhall rot.</hi> We read in the <hi>6th</hi> of <hi>Gen.</hi> of <hi>Giants in the earth,</hi> mighty men, and men of Renown; Giants in ſtature, and Giants in nature; Giants in ſtate, condition, and quality in the world, and Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants too in wickedneſs; but there is not one of their names mentioned in all the Scripture. <hi>Abel,</hi> and <hi>Seth,</hi> and <hi>Enos,</hi> and <hi>Cainan,</hi> and <hi>Mahaliel,</hi> and <hi>Jared,</hi> and <hi>Methuſala,</hi> and <hi>Lamech,</hi> and <hi>Noah:</hi> Theſe have their names recorded, and perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated with honour from the beginning of the world, to the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:98090:11"/> end thereof, while theſe Giants in wickedneſs, both perſons and names are gone down in ſilence, and buried in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>and of forgetfulneſs. We read the names of many ſinners that are mentioned in Holy Writ, but with ſhame enough. Of bloody <hi>Cain;</hi> of hunting <hi>Nimrod;</hi> of hard-hearted <hi>Pharaoh;</hi> of a painted <hi>Jezabel;</hi> of an incorrigible <hi>Ahab;</hi> of proud <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod;</hi> of an ambitious <hi>Diotrophes:</hi> But what are theſe to a Martyr <hi>Abel?</hi> To a righteous <hi>Noah,</hi> A faithful <hi>Abraham,</hi> A plain-hearted <hi>Jacob,</hi> A meek <hi>Moſes,</hi> a zealous <hi>Phineas;</hi> A pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Samuel,</hi> A patient <hi>Job,</hi> A penitent <hi>Peter?</hi> Let men boaſt and glory, and brag of their birth, and power, and wit, and authority, and dignity, and preferment: Let them boaſt of theſe: true Religion is the true honour. <hi>Abel</hi> being dead, yet ſpeaketh; and being dead, he is yet ſpoken of.</p>
            <p>We have now ſpoken to the Text as it is in it ſelf. Let us now apply it to our occaſion; That dead Saints do yet ſpeak, that is the general truth to which we have hitherto ſpoken in the particular inſtance of <hi>Abel:</hi> but inſtances of this kind and nature are more than one. Let us ſpeak therefore to the general truth again in another inſtance; invert only the name, change <hi>Abel</hi> for <hi>Newcomen,</hi> and read the Text of him; <hi>he being dead, yet ſpeaketh.</hi> Being dead, did I ſay? What, art thou dead, Oh thou bleſſed ſoul! Oh! killing, wounding word! could I bleed for thee! thou whom God was pleaſed to ſeparate from thy Mothers womb, and to call by his Grace, that he might reveal his Grace in thee, that thou mighteſt preach the everlaſting Goſpel to the world of ſinners. Thou that wert commiſſionated to be Chriſts Ambaſſador, in his name to beſeech ſinners to be reconciled to God: Thou a Scribe inſtructed to the Kingdom of Heaven; that broughteſt out of thy treaſury things both new and old: Thou whoſe natural gifts and abilities were like <hi>Aarons</hi> Plate of pure Gold upon thy breaſt, whereon <hi>holineſs to the Lord</hi> was ingraven. Thou, who (<hi>Iſaiah</hi> like) hadſt the Tongue of the learned, and touched with a Coal from Gods Altar, who kneweſt how
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98090:12"/> to ſpeak a word in ſeaſon to the weary. Thou that (like <hi>Paul</hi>) wert brought up at the feet of <hi>Gamaliel;</hi> and more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over inſtructed, as he by a light from Heaven. Thou a gliſtering, glorious ſtar in the right hand of God. Thou that wert the Angel of God to this his Church. Art thou dead? Thou the deſire of thouſands! The dearly beloved and long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for, the joy and crown of thy generation? Thou on whoſe face ſo many eyes were fixed. Thou on whoſe lips ſo many ears were hanged; at whoſe windows ſo many Doves have flocked. Thou at whoſe ſilence ſo many hearts were broken. Thou at whoſe departure into a foreign Land, ſo many tears were ſhed, and hands wrung: Art thou dead? Thou whoſe tongue was as choice ſilver, whoſe lips fed ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. Thou whoſe Doctrine fell as the rain. Whoſe life ſhined as the light. Whoſe zeal provoked others. Whoſe labours bliſſed the Earth. Whoſe prayers pierced the Heavens. Thou at whoſe preſence the bold Sinners bluſhed. At whoſe thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derings ſecure conſciences were awakened. Thou at whoſe ſearchings the Hypocrite trembled. Thou at whoſe force the Kingdom of darkneſs ſhaked, and the powers of Hell fell. Thou who haſt bound up many a broken heart, with thy tender and skilful hand. Thou who haſt carried the Lambs in thy arms: A ſpiritual Father of ſo many Children. The happy inſtrument of life in ſo many dead ſouls. Art thou dead? Oh, could the love-lines of thy perſon, the uſefulneſs of thy gifts, the willingneſs of thy heart to thy Maſters ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, the neceſſity of the Church, the prayers of the Saints, the love of thy Friends, the deſire of thy Relations, could this have prevailed, we had not ſaid of thee this day, <hi>Thou art dead.</hi> Verily thou art the tryal of our faith. Thou art the exerciſe of our patience and contentation. How hardly do we reſtrain our reaſonings and complainings to the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? What a multitude is the wicked, ungodly, violent, intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate, prophane, blaſphemous generation? The very curſe and peſt, and burden of the earth they tread upon; the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98090:12"/> earth groaneth under them; hell gapeth for them; and heaven is darkned by them. And ſhall theſe live, and thou dye! What mercenary hirelings and greedy wolves are crept into the Church of God, not regarding, nor ſparing the flock: unſavoury ſalt, fitter for the dunghil. Shall theſe live, and thou dye? What dark corners require light! What hungry ſouls are craving for bread! What deſolate Congregations mourn in ſilence! And is this a time for thee to dye? But <hi>righteous art thou, O Lord, and we will not plead with thee concerning thy judgments:</hi> this is the will of our heavenly Father, and <hi>thy will be done.</hi> Thou art gone, oh precious and deſired <hi>Newcomen:</hi> Thy courſe is finiſhed, thy race is run, thy work is done: this place that knew thee Twenty years, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, ſhall know thee no more: this Pulpit ſhall ſound forth, and theſe walls ſhall eccho back thy voice no more. This Congregation ſhall receive the law at thy mouth no more; but our eyes ſhall weep for thee, when we ſee thee not; and our tongues ſhall ſpeak of thee, when we hear thee not. May our feet follow thee, though we reach thee not? May we go to thee, that canſt not return to us? But re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collect thy ſelf, oh my paſſionate ſoul! whither ſhall affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on carry thee? Wipe thine eyes from tears, and read on the Text; this ſecond word ſhall extenuate the firſt: He is dead; but <hi>being dead, he yet ſpeaketh.</hi> Theſe be the laſt words of <hi>David,</hi> ſaith the holy Pen-man of the book of <hi>Samuel.</hi> And thus were the laſt words of <hi>Reverend Newcomen.</hi> Shall the ſtanders by report, and ſay they were? no, for he <hi>yet ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</hi> You remember his dying words, his parting words, which <hi>viva voce,</hi> from this place he delivered to this Congregation, and out of that dear love he had unto this Congregation; and that his dying words might make the deeper impreſſion, he afterwards committed them to perpetual memory; and this is the name by which he called them, his <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ltimum vale:</hi> But my Text ſhall blot out that: that was not his laſt <hi>fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel;</hi> for being dead, he yet ſpeaketh. He ſpeaketh,</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:98090:13"/>
            <p>Firſt, From a Forreign Land to his Native Countrey: Oh dear <hi>England!</hi> In thee my Mother conceived and brought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e forth. In thee I drew my firſt breath. In thee I hung up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my Mothers breaſts. In thee I was nouriſhed, and fed, and cloathed, and had all things pertaining unto life. In thee I had a liberal, ingenious, and religious education. In thee the name of Chriſt was put upon me. In thee I ſaw a glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous light, and heard the ſound of the Goſpel. In thee it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God to call me effectually by his Grace. In thee, God judging me faithful, put me into the Miniſtry. In thee I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed many years of precious liberty of ſerving God in the Goſpel of his Son. In thee I have begotten many ſpiritual children unto God. In thee I enjoyed ſweet communion with God and his Saints. This was thy bounty, and this was thy bleſſing, and this was it which endeared thee to me. This is the bond that did conſtrain my heart to love thee. This is the foundation of my moſt enlarged and improved diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged duty to thee. Now from this unfeigned and invincible love, and from the conſcience of this my bounden duty, I have faithfully ſerved thy welfare and happineſs. I have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded and ſet before thee peace; that peace may be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thy walls, and proſperity within thy Palaces, was the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of my heart to God, and the endeavour of my hand. In the day when thou hadſt ſinned, I was aſhamed for thee, and bare the burden of thy ſins before my God. I wept in ſecret for thy pride, and ſighed for the abominations that were found in thee, and entreated for thee. In the day when thou ſufferedſt, I mourned. <hi>When thou wert ſick, my cloathing was ſackcloath, I humbled my ſoul with faſting, and my prayer was in thy calamity.</hi> When thou rejoicedſt, I rejoiced with thee; I went with the multitude to give thanks, and to keep holy day: I gave thanks for thee in the great Congregation, and I praiſed God for thee among much people. Where thou wert ignorant, I endeavoured to enlighten thee. Where thou wert wandering, I endeavoured to reduce thee. Where thou
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:98090:13"/> wert offending, I endeavoured to reform thee. My Cloſet, my Study, my Books, my Pulpit, Publick Aſſemblies, mine own and other Families, can bear witneſs for me how I have ſpent, and been ſpent, watched, and prayed, and faſted, and ſtudied, and laboured in the word and doctrine; how I have preached the word in ſeaſon, and out of ſeaſon, reproving, rebuking with long ſuffering. Now my dear Countrey, what have I done unto thee? Wherein have I offended thee? What is my iniquity and my ſin? Is my zeal for Reformation, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of pure and undefiled Religion, the forfeiture of my liberty, that thou haſt caſt me out of thy Vineyard, and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned me out of the Harveſt, that my mouth muſt be ſhut up in ſilence, that I muſt never ſpeak more to thee in the name of the Lord? Have I not reaſon to ſay, For my love thou haſt been my enemy? Thou haſt requited me evil for good, and hatred for my good will. Through thy unkindneſs my gray hairs are brought down with ſorrow to the grave in a ſtrange Land.</p>
            <p>More particularly, He being dead, yet ſpeaketh:</p>
            <p n="1">1. He ſpeaketh firſt to you my <hi>Brethren the Miniſters</hi> of the Goſpel, and to my ſelf. He ſpeaketh,</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Having put your hands to the Plough, look not back.</hi> Lay not up your Talent in a Napkin. Never think of being diſcharged from the Miniſtry of the Goſpel, or the ſervice of the Goſpel, by God. Hath God intruſted you with gifts? Hath God called us to the Miniſtry? Hath he made us Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards of his Myſteries? Surely he will find us work, he will give us opportunities to diſpence his Word, he will ſhew us where to ſow our ſeed. <hi>No man having lighted a Candle, putteth it under a buſhel, but ſets it on a Candleſtick. The ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifestation of the Spirit is given to profit withall.</hi> Therefore the Providence of God that ſhut his mouth in one place, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened it in another.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He ſpeaketh unto us: <hi>Natural and acquired abilities are needful accompliſhments for the work of the Ministry.</hi> He had
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:98090:14"/> in his treaſury things both new and old; the old things of Nature as well as the new things of grace, and both together made him an able Miniſter of the New-Teſtament: by this then he ſpeaketh unto us as <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy,</hi> 1 Tim. 4.13, <hi>Be thou an example to the believers in word, in converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in ſpirit, in faith, in charity, in purity. Give attendance to reading, to exhortation, to doctrine.</hi> And 2 Tim. 2.15, <hi>Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to ſhew thy ſelf approved, a workman that needeth not to be aſhamed.</hi> He that will be a Workman in the Miniſtry that needeth not to be aſhamed, muſt be a Student: Grace is profitable to our ſelves, but gifts are not to be expected immediately by God now as in the Primitive Church, but in the uſe of means.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He ſpeaketh unto Miniſters; <hi>Diligence, painfulneſs and faithfulneſs, are incumbent upon the Miniſters of the Goſpel.</hi> His great example ſpeaks this, of which this place wherein we are do bear him ample witneſs. The difficulty of the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, the concernment of precious ſouls, the certainty and ſtrictneſs of the accompt that muſt be given, are ſtrong ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments to provoke to labour in the Word and Doctrine. Then doth he ſpeak to us, as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.6, <hi>Stir up the gift that is in thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. He ſpeaketh yet again unto us Miniſters, <hi>That the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers Doctrine muſt be exemplified by the Miniſters life.</hi> So did his great example ſpeak, he did as well live as ſpeak the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine that he preached; not like the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> Mat. 29.23, <hi>That ſaid and did not.</hi> And then he ſpeaks again, as <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy, Be thou an example to the believers, in word, in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, in converſation, in charity, in faith, in purity.</hi> And as Chriſt to his Apoſtles, <hi>You are the light of the world: Let your light ſo ſhine before men, that others ſeeing your good works, may glorifie your Father which is in heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. And laſtly, He ſpeaketh unto us Miniſters, <hi>Love, pity, compaſſion to precious ſouls.</hi> Earneſt, eager deſires of their
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:98090:14"/> ſalvation: this is a powerful Motive and Principle to be la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borious in Doctrine, and exemplary in Life: this was his Motive, herein he excelled. His dear love to this Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation fixed him immoveably in this Candleſtick, from which no diſcouragement whatſoever at home on the one hand, nor no temptation from abroad on the other, could ever unſettle him, till removed by a power not to be reſiſted: His labours were the labour of love: It was love that moved Chriſt the great Shepherd and Biſhop of Souls, to lay down his life for the ſheep; and the ſame principle of love will move the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-ſhepherds to lay out their lives, to ſpend and be ſpent, and to call nothing dear or precious, that may contribute to the ſaving of a ſoul.</p>
            <p>He ſpeaketh again, being dead, unto this Congregation. What ſpeaks he unto you? He ſpeaks this:</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>While you have the light, walk in the light;</hi> while you have the light, improve it; make uſe of a faithful Miniſter, while you hear his voice, and ſee his face: he is not a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual bleſſing; he is not always to be with you. The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets do not live for ever; <hi>I have,</hi> ſaith he to you, <hi>ſpoken to you in the Name of the Lord: but now you ſhall ſee my face, and hear my voice no more.</hi> If God betruſt you with a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Miniſter, make uſe of him while you have him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He being dead, ſpeaks to this Congregation: The <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitency of peoples hearts, and incorrigibleneſs</hi> of peoples lives, may ſtop the mouth, may cut off the life of a faithful Paſtor. May I not (beloved) without breach of charity adviſe you to enquire whether <hi>Dedham's</hi> ſins did not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reave <hi>Dedham</hi> of a faithful Paſtor? Is it not the Judgment that God threatned upon the Vineyard that did not anſwer his tillage, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.6, <hi>I will command the Clouds that they rain no rain upon it?</hi> And is it not the judgment God threatned to rebellious <hi>Iſrael?</hi> Ezek. 3, <hi>Thou ſhalt be dumb, and ſhalt be no more a reprover to them, for they are a rebellious houſe.</hi> Yet withal he ſpeaks, that God is very loath to execute ſuch
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:98090:15"/> a Judgment upon a diſobedient and unbelieving people. How loath was God to remove your Paſtor from you? By degrees he executed it, or at leaſt not all at once: he ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped his mouth firſt, that he ſhould not ſpeak, but you ſaw his face. Then God removed his perſon, that you ſhould not ſee his face, but he had communion with you by his Letters; but now God hath removed him far away, that there ſhall be no more ſeeing of his face, nor hearing of his voice, nor any communication between him and you in this world.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He being dead, yet ſpeaks to this Congregation, <hi>Ded<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, thy account is great, ſee that thou diſcharge it well;</hi> thou art not in an equal ſtate with other places, but like <hi>Caper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naum;</hi> haſt been lifted up to Heaven; and he can ſay as <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> Acts 20.19,20, <hi>You know from the firſt day that I came among you, after what manner I have been among you, at all ſeaſons: ſerving the Lord with all humility of mind, and with many tears and temptations; and how I kept back nothing that was profitable unto you, but have ſhewed you, and have taught you publickly, and from houſe to houſe.</hi> Now having lived under the Miniſtry of ſo worthy, ſo able, and ſo faithful a Paſtor, your account is great. To whom much is given, of him much ſhall be required; and he that knows <hi>his Maſters will, and doth it not, ſhall be beaten with many ſtripes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. He being dead, ſpeaks to this Congregation: <hi>Hold out the profeſſion of your faith with patience and conſtancy.</hi> His example ſpeaks: What faith I have taught you, I have aſſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, I have teſtified, I have ſealed by my Sufferings; ſee now that you keep it, that you loſe it not, by <hi>treachery,</hi> or <hi>cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. He being dead, ſpeaks to this Congregation. <hi>Have the Miniſtry of Gods faithful ſervants been effectual for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, edification, ſalvation of any ſoul, let him give God the glory.</hi> Thus he ſpeaks again, as <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians, We have this treaſury in earthen veſſels, that the excellency of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:98090:15"/> the power may be of God, and not of men.</hi> It was not his gifts and graces, his pains and induſtry that wrought grace in any of the hearts of his people, but this was the <hi>power of God;</hi> he was an <hi>earthen veſſel,</hi> but now is broken; and the word he ſpoke, was not the word of a meer mortal man, but of the everliving God that <hi>endures for ever,</hi> that God may have the glory of his converting mercy.</p>
            <p n="6">6. He being dead, yet ſpeaks to this Congregation: <hi>Weep not for me, but weep for your ſelves.</hi> I would not propheſie of evil things: but who can tell but ſome dreadful Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may be at hand: ſome dreadful Judgment may hang over the head of <hi>England,</hi> and this righteous man may be <hi>taken away from the evil to come.</hi> Who knoweth but God hath ſaid to him, <hi>Thou ſhalt dye in peace, and ſhalt not ſee all the evil that I will bring upon the land of thy Nativity?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. He ſpeaketh unto all, and that he ſpeaks is this: <hi>The te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of a good conſcience, the power of faith, the joy of Gods ſalvation overcometh the very King of terrors.</hi> So far was this holy man of God from the fear of death, that in the ſight and preſence of it, with his dart ready to ſtrike him to the heart, he begins to ſing his heavenly <hi>Hellelujah. He died in full aſſurance, and great joy, in the ſight of Heaven, in the very arms and embraces of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, He being dead, yet ſpeaketh: he ſpeaks unto God. He <hi>ſpeaketh unto God</hi> by his <hi>cryes and ſupplications:</hi> his fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent prayers are continually before God; before that God that heareth prayers: His prayers ſpeak to God for the Church of God in general: His prayers ſpeak to God for this <hi>Church</hi> in particular; the Church whereof we are all Members. And more eſpecially his prayers are before God for this place; the Souls that were his charge. His ardent entire affection prompted his moſt earneſt cryes to Heaven for their ſalvation.</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>Abel,</hi> being dead, yet ſpeaketh. Thus <hi>Newcomen, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dead, yet ſpeaketh.</hi> Now may God hear the dead that
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:98090:16"/> ſpeak: And may we hear the dead that ſpeak? That when the dead that ſpeak, ſhall ſpeak again, and hear again, as one day they ſhall; we may alſo hear with them the voice of the <hi>Archangel,</hi> the <hi>ſound of the trumpet,</hi> the voice of the Son of God that ſhall raiſe them and us from the dead, and the voice of the Son of God upon the Throne, ſaying, <hi>Well done good and faithful ſervant, enter thou into the joy of thy Lord. Come ye bleſſed of my Father, inherit the Kingdom prepared for you, from the foundation of the World.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:98090:16"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
